<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Personal homepage.</description>
    <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ozan.ogreden.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 23:12:23 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 23:12:23 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>No-CV</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For years, one of the most prominent elements on this page has been a link to my CV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, the same will be there but will read “no-CV” and will link to this page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This comes from the realization that when I think of my CV, I think of a different thing than most. I would like to take &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; to my work. As this is my “CV”, it makes more sense for me to link you to it: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ozan.ogreden.com&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, which isn’t in a good state, but that’s not how it will stay!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/15</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/15</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Spaced Repetition, Flinches / Ugh-Fields</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;About 15 months ago. I have started (re-)using Anki for expanding my Dutch vocabulary. After a few months of dutiful daily Anki practices, it had become a dull exercise. My search for Anki-revival tactics led me to Michael Nielsen’s essay &lt;a href=&quot;http://augmentingcognition.com/ltm.html&quot;&gt;Augmenting Long-term Memory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Anki for topics other than language has been an interesting experience. For instance, engaging with a topic/material at regular but not always predictable intervals has been emotionally pleasing for me. This venue is actively researched by Andy Matuschak and you should check &lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.andymatuschak.org/About_these_notes?stackedNotes=zUw5PuD8op9oq8kHvni6sug6eRTNtR9Wqma&amp;amp;stackedNotes=z4rRX3qwSSJRsEkdXKwH2shamgHNeRthrMLiF&quot;&gt;his work&lt;/a&gt; out if you’re into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just today I’ve run into a radically interesting use case at the intersection of spaced repetition and mental health. Internet is a small world, so this happens to be located on a blog that I distinctly remember visiting earlier: &lt;a href=&quot;http://becomingeden.com/developing-object-permanence-around-flinches/&quot;&gt;becomingeden.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/04/11/very-recently/&quot;&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--[[202104112132 (very) recently - post]]--&gt;, today has been generous with inspiring stuff, too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/13</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/13</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>EBS for individuals</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve read Joel Spolsky’s Evidence Based Scheduling a while ago, thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.beeminder.com/t/20th-anniversary-of-the-joel-test-for-software-teams/7096/25&quot;&gt;a discussion&lt;/a&gt; in Beeminder forums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s written from the developer team management perspective. In it’s essence, Evidence Based Scheduling calibrates developers’ estimation performance so that realistic estimates can be obtained. (A key aspect of the method is that it also quantifies the confidence one may have in an estimate, but that’s besides the point.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think EBS may also be useful from the individual perspective. In the practice suggested by Joel, “velocities” that are older than 6 months discarded since estimators get better at estimating. Someone who’s early in their career could also get noticably better and faster in such a time span. A side effect of EBS data would then be making explicit if “5 story points” came to mean 8 days to 4 days, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/12</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/12</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>(Very) recently</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tmcw&quot;&gt;Tom MacWright’s&lt;/a&gt; Recently series, and to appease &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beeminder.com/oguzhanogreden/w-posted&quot;&gt;Beeminder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes-for-junior-developers&quot;&gt;Notes for junior developers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be starting working as a developer next week. As in any problem solving domain, problems I will get will have a few good and many bad solutions. My focus in this “first period” will be focusing on learning what makes a solution good, and when to make a trade-off for a worse solution for the sake of e.g. speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing problem solving expertise is difficult. Surely, I will feel lost, tried and tried, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainpickings.org/2012/10/15/when-charles-darwin-hated-everybody/&quot;&gt;hate everybody &amp;amp; everything&lt;/a&gt;. Here’s some advice from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dulcedejae/status/1366698180340047874&quot;&gt;jae anne&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dan_abramov/status/1366728171534565376&quot;&gt;Dan Abramov&lt;/a&gt; on how to tackle this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, jae anne shouts a warning that anytime something works but you don’t understand it, you should treat it as it’s “not working” and your work not done. You just don’t give into the feeling of “I just want this damn thing to be done.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a sense, these are obvious. In another sense, it’s hard for me to tell “Up to which resolution should &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; understand what’s going on here?” before being able to use jae anne’s suggestion. That’s easier to do for me than following their advice, and is a pre-requisite too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;command-line-tools-that-compete-with-a-hadoop-cluster&quot;&gt;Command-line tools that compete with a Hadoop Cluster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam Drake wrote (many years ago) &lt;a href=&quot;https://adamdrake.com/command-line-tools-can-be-235x-faster-than-your-hadoop-cluster.html&quot;&gt;a short demo&lt;/a&gt; of what can be achieved with &lt;a href=&quot;https://brandur.org/small-sharp-tools&quot;&gt;small, sharp tools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty happy if I can pipe &lt;a href=&quot;https://parkbee.github.io/data-til/2020/11/05/find-and-replace-extension-regex/&quot;&gt;two shell commands&lt;/a&gt; (and not lose any file), while Adam goes on to parallelize operations and all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspiring stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shorthand-for-shaping&quot;&gt;“Shorthand for shaping”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always found shorthand a bit magical. In my own way, I have about 7 shortcuts defined for &lt;a href=&quot;https://espanso.org&quot;&gt;espanso&lt;/a&gt;. That’s all I have to say about shorthand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also custom (sometimes ad-hoc) shorthands that people use. Ryan Singer’s essay &lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/rjs/9-shorthand-for-shaping-cc672da1&quot;&gt;“Shorthand for shaping”&lt;/a&gt; is a short exposition of a custom shorthand of how he used a simple shorthand notation for thinking about a early stage design process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being someone who doesn’t know shorthand, neither designs anything, I found it pretty interesting to see that a sketch like this is part of the process:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021-04-11-very-recently.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/2021/04/11/very-recently/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/2021/04/11/very-recently/</guid>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Looking for: Meta blub studies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Blub studies is not a very good &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2016/02/20/writing-advice/&quot;&gt;concept-handle&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not very clear what “blub” is. It is, however, a great meme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its shortest definition, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.benkuhn.net/blub/&quot;&gt;blub studies&lt;/a&gt; is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the study of what goes on in the guts of these boring, everyday systems–not the kind you get tenure for inventing, but the kind people actually use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben Kuhn suggests “kickstarting ‘your blub flywheel’” however you can. He promises it will eventually pay off greatly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an appetite for blub studies. And this sounds like a good advice to me.  I will heed it. Just like I followed the “Use Vim emulation in an IDE” advice, as a person with an appetite for keyboard-dominant interaction with my computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like there’s something missing. There must be a “blub-studies studies” level that we can rise to. At that level, we could ask and answer questions like: How to build appetite for blub-studies? How to get better at it? I don’t think I have come across this yet. Except perhaps in The Zen and Motorcycle Maintenance, or Philosophical Explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This came my way thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca&quot;&gt;Julia Evans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--[[202104041301 Julia Evans]]--&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/08</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/08</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ghulheim, a drawing by Neil Gaiman</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Even from the path below Ghûlheim, even from miles away, Bod could see that all of the angles were wrong–that the walls sloped crazily, that it was every nightmare he had ever endured made into a place, like a huge mouth of jutting teeth. It was a city that had been built just to be abandoned, in which all the fears and madnesses and revulsions of the creatures who built it were made into stone. The ghoul-folk had found it and delighted in it and called it home. &lt;em&gt;(The Graveyard Book, Neil Gaiman)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a great description. I could attempt at a good sketch how Ghûlheim looks, and likely fail to caricaturize how Evil it looks. The wickedness of the city Neil Gaiman describes  is as pointy as it needs to be: it’s a good specimen of the familiar &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=dark+scary+town+illustration&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwj7mPHetufvAhXN2rsIHddlAZoQ2-cCegQIABAA&quot;&gt;Dark Scary Town Illustration&lt;/a&gt; with a touch of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=dark%20scary%20town%20illustration%20tim%20burton&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;tbs=rimg:CZ1leCtb2WFyYRNZA6gyR6Tg&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0CAIQrnZqFwoTCJj79tS35-8CFQAAAAAdAAAAABAC&amp;amp;biw=1265&amp;amp;bih=1313&quot;&gt;Tim Burton aesthetics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/05</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/05</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to notice what you don't know?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some authors make you feel lucky that you’re in their audience. &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca&quot;&gt;Julia Evans&lt;/a&gt; &lt;!--[[202104041301 Julia Evans]]--&gt; is one of those authors for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julia recently published &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca/blog/learn-how-things-work/&quot;&gt;“Get better at programming by learning how things work”&lt;/a&gt;. She has great advice that pairs well with Peter Norvig’s &lt;!--[[202104041304 Peter Norvig]]--&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://norvig.com/21-days.html&quot;&gt;recipe for programming success&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One question that she leaves open is “How do you figure out what you don’t know?” Here’s what’s been working for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to talk about the topic opens the portal for me. I find self-talking out loud effective. Initiating the talk with a hypothetical interview question is helpful here. For instance, “Can you explain how a Flexbox is laid out in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QcUey-DVYjk&quot;&gt;5 levels&lt;/a&gt;?” If can come up with two levels, perhaps three, but not more, that’s a good sign. That usually tells me I’m at the “I can use this thing (and it will be okay).” level, borrowing Julia’s description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I have the portal open, I need a good source. Then I’ll just read it with a specific goal: To make notes of concepts I don’t know, or statements that I wouldn’t be able to make myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the CSS example, I thought I’d be able to add another level by reading the CSS specification. (I was also curious why people seemed “scared” of them.) This was a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how it worked. A sentence &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/css-flexbox-1/#flex-containers&quot;&gt;like&lt;/a&gt; “A flex container establishes a new flex formatting context for its contents. This is the same as establishing a block formatting context, except that flex layout is used instead of block layout.” brought up the following question:  What is a formatting context? I also noticed that I should probably know how block containers establish their formatting context. Or what kind of formatting context they establish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another example. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/css-flexbox-1/#visibility-collapse&quot;&gt;Reading&lt;/a&gt; “Though collapsed flex items aren’t rendered, they do appear in the formatting structure.” highlighted box in my mental model that I need to fill in. What is a formatting structure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, this can get scary: The amount of notes I now have is overwhelming. Next to that, stepping into unknown territory makes one thing very hard: To make smart choices to reach your goal effectively. Which of this leads should I follow? At this point, I usually just make notes, and keep reading. I read until I have a sense of which leads are promising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could, of course, heed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/Style/CSS/read.en.html&quot;&gt;the advice of the wise&lt;/a&gt; and learn everything. But that seems impractical for my needs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/04</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/04</guid>
        
        
        <category>notebook</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Margaret Atwood's Foreword to The Graveyard Book</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The 10th anniversary edition of The Graveyard Book has a foreword by Margaret Atwood. The foreword is delightful. And it’s short. In five pages, she succinctly meanders through all I want from a forward: literary context, Gaiman’s place in that context, excitement about the story, and even a personal anectode that involved Gaiman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me try to give you a taste of the meandering yet to the point style of Atwood. Here’s where she makes a leap towards introducing the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Astrologically, Neil Gaiman is a Scorpio with Gemini rising, and, if you go in for that sort of thing - as he must, because I found his horoscope online - this explains much. Scorpio is governed by Pluto, patron of the Underworld as well as of plumbing, underwear, the criminal underworld, and everything below the line; and Gemini is ruled by Mercury or Hermes, god of thieves, jokes, communication, travel, and secrets; in addition to which he is the conductor of souls to the Underworld. Most travel to the land of the dead is one-way, but Hermes comes and goes as he pleases, and so do various protagonists in books by Neil Gaiman, including this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following paragraph opens with “Most of us have a distinct aversion to being dead. We have great difficulty imagining ourselves as simply not existing anymore: […]”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet we have tried to imagine this throuhout the history. Atwood then surveys a selection of ancient stories that attempt at an explanation and reminds: “But there are many other possibilities. […] It is this latter body of folklore that Neil Gaiman draws upon for The Graveyard Book.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fantastic!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/02</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/02</guid>
        
        
        <category>notebook</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evaluation of LINQ can be deferred past the moment DbContext is disposed.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;That the .NET Core ecosystem brings the Language-Integrated Query (LINQ) of C# and Entity Framework Core provides a lot of comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One property of LINQ is that it defers execution of queries, if the return value of the query is a sequence of values.
This provides for flexibility in composing complex queries programatically without changing the way you compose the query.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some pitfalls of deferred execution, for instance it can cause degraded performance due to potential multiple enumeration.
I learned of another one that caught me by surprise:
If the execution is deferred long enough, resources that are needed for querying may be &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/api/system.idisposable?view=net-5.0&quot;&gt;disposed&lt;/a&gt; of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Searching the internet for “The operation cannot be completed because the DbContext has been disposed.” returns more than enough results, &lt;a href=&quot;The operation cannot be completed because the DbContext has been disposed&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is one StackOverflow answer that I found useful.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/til/deferred-execution-lazy-evaluation-disposed-error</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/til/deferred-execution-lazy-evaluation-disposed-error</guid>
        
        <category>ef-core</category>
        
        
        <category>til</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Improving readability on web with typography basics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What does your visitors first do when they land your webpage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you what I do. I press down &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Command&lt;/code&gt; and hit &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; two times. Unless your page already looks like &lt;a href=&quot;https://ia.net&quot;&gt;iA’s home page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;post-image&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px solid rgba(0, 134, 179, 0.15);&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021-03-24-ia-light.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to represent how large those letters actually are with a screenshot.
(Especially since I stole their background color ;))
They are really large, go check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out, I’m not alone in my discontent about font size on web.
This became only more clear as I starting reading about web typography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some basic rules that I learned, that improved readability on this page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we start, &lt;strong&gt;a warning&lt;/strong&gt;: Writing about typography on a blog that’s still so poorly laid is a bit… painful.
Reading will be even more so.
I’m moving away from the Jekyll theme I started with, but things are in transition, so bear with me ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-its-a-matter-of-established-principles-not-taste&quot;&gt;1. It’s a matter of established principles, not taste.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You might ask “Why not just allow the user to choose the type size?” Well, adjusting type size is not a matter of taste, but a matter of reading distance. Since most websites and applications have an overly small type size, new customers would initially choose a type size that they are used to, that is: too small a size […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ia.net/topics/responsive-typography-the-basics&quot;&gt;Responsive Typography: The Basics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--[[202103162148 responsive typography the basics]]--&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oliver Reichenstein &lt;!--[[202103192305 Oliver Reichenstein]]--&gt; is quite clear in his post.
More about how to choose the size in a bit.
Before that… why in the first place did we get used to uncomfortably small type sizes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the answer is seems to be a bad alignment of stars in the industry.
Richard Rutter &lt;a href=&quot;https://alistapart.com/article/howtosizetextincss/#section3&quot;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt; that 16 pixels was often considered too large&lt;!--[[202103182126 how to size text in CSS]]--&gt;.
I’m not if this is still the case.
But in any case, if Rutter didn’t get what he wanted, it’s not surprising that most of the designers couldn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the default of 16 pixels seemed a good &lt;em&gt;starting point&lt;/em&gt; to me.
Starting there, I used the practical trick offered by Reichenstein:
Take a book and hold it at a comfortable reading distance.
Simultaneously, hold your digital device at it’s common use distance.
Make sure the physical sizes of letters are the same.
That is the correct size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this blog, I’ve chosen &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; sizes to base my typographic scales: 1.12rem and 1.25rem, for mobile and desktop.
Without overwriting the root font size, that’d be based on 16 pixels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-choose-a-modular-scale-not-one-size&quot;&gt;2. Choose a modular scale, not one size.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the sixteenth century, a series of common sizes developed among European typographers, and the series survived with little change and few additions for 400 years. […] Use the old familiar scale, or use new scales of your own devising, but limit yourself, at first, to a modest set of distinct and related intervals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Elements_of_Typographic_Style&quot;&gt;Elements of Typographic Style&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--[[202103160852 elements of typography]]--&gt;, quoted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://webtypography.net/3.1.1&quot;&gt;Elements of Typography Applied To Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--[[202103182109 elements of typography applied to web]]--&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is a “scale” when it comes to typography?
Well, it’s quiet similar to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scale_(music)&quot;&gt;musical scale&lt;/a&gt;.
It’s a series of numbers that make up a coherent set around a base size.
The coherence provided by the scale helps your layout “make sense” to the observers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way of defining a typographic scale is choosing a “base size” and a multiplier, giving you a “modular scale”.
The multiplier defines the ratio of each point in the scale to the next.
For instance, a base size of 16px and a ratio of 2 would give you the scale: …, 4, 8, 16, 32, 64, … 
One idea that I liked is that you can use the scale for determining not only the size of font elements, but also designing the whitespace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Brown’s&lt;!--[[202103182201 Tim Brown]]--&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.modularscale.com&quot;&gt;modularscale.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--[[202103182200 modularscale.com]]--&gt; is a nice tool for choosing (and quickly implementing) modular scales.
How to choose the ratio? In his post &lt;a href=&quot;https://alistapart.com/article/more-meaningful-typography/&quot;&gt;More Meaningful Typography&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;!--[[202103192149 More Meaningful Typography]]--&gt; Tim Brown gives an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I chose the golden mean (1:1.618). It is a beautiful proportion with historical and cultural connections that make sense for the typefaces I’ve chosen and the text I’m setting. Although it is a contemporary design, Minion draws upon Renaissance ideals […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a designer, and neither am I well versed in typography.
So I find such judgements hard to make.
For this blog, I’ve chosen two ratios: 1:1.06 for mobile and 1:1.2 for desktop, primarily because they looked fine for some spacing I want to implement soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-use-unitless-responsive-line-heights&quot;&gt;3. Use unitless, responsive line heights.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Frank Chimero&lt;!--[[202103211711 Frank Chimero]]--&gt;, you can have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://frankchimero.com/blog/2020/redesign-this-design/&quot;&gt;“blog that’s superior to most with a couple lines of CSS”&lt;/a&gt;. One of those few lines is the CSS declaration: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;line-height: 1.5&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal line line height for &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; blog, however, also depends on the reading distance, like the base font size.
The key thing here seems to be that the line height should help “promote horizontal movement” and make the lines of text feel like “horizontal lines, not woven fabric”, as noted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2014/09/balancing-line-length-font-size-responsive-web-design/&quot;&gt;Laura Franz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--[[202103232057 Size Matters Balancing the line length and font size in responsive design]]--&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the implementation side, the most surprising thing for me was the importance of &lt;a href=&quot;/til/using-unitless-lineheights-css&quot;&gt;using unitless line-heights&lt;/a&gt;,
as noted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://meyerweb.com/eric/thoughts/2006/02/08/unitless-line-heights/&quot;&gt;Eric Meyer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found 1.9rem and 2.03rem to play nicely with mobile and desktop settings I’ve mentioned so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;there-is-more&quot;&gt;There is more…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you made it so far, here’s one more thing: the “measure”. Traditional wisdom suggests that your line width (or measure) should be 45-75 characters, or about 10 words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a bit wider than 75 characters satisfying. And both Laura Franz (in her above linked blog post) and the iA folks (as reflected in their current choices) seem to agree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While choosing the measure, I found Vasilis van Gemert’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://vasilis.nl/nerd//code/measure-help/&quot;&gt;“international measure slider”&lt;/a&gt; and Chris Coyier’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://css-tricks.com/bookmarklet-colorize-text-45-75-characters-line-length-testing/&quot;&gt;bookmarklet&lt;/a&gt; to colorize 45-75 character range of text elements text run very helpful in being mindful about how precisely I went against traditional wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that these tools make it more enjoyable to play with typography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, this is a field where our perceptual abilities, representation capacities of our devices and fanciful aesthetic judgements clash and combine. Reading about it, tinkering with a few tools, and then making up one’s own rules is a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/2021/03/24/typography-font-size-scale-line-height/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/2021/03/24/typography-font-size-scale-line-height/</guid>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
