<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Personal homepage.</description>
    <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ozan.ogreden.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 23:18:01 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 23:18:01 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Advice reversal, again</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I asked a friend of mine to review my post &lt;a href=&quot;/notebook/2021/04/26&quot;&gt;“On ‘The Art of Doing Science and Engineering’”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--[[202104262127 On The Art of Doing Science and Engineering]]--&gt; for me. One of the questions she had for me was “So do we want to understand the maths or not?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one sense, the point I tried to make with the earlier post was the familiar “advice reversal advice” in disguise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone could advise used Hamming’s example on “Why it matters to be able to predict the future?” in two directions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is well known the drunken sailor who staggers to the left or right with \(n\) independent random steps will, on the average, end up about \(\sqrt n\) steps from the origin. But if there is a pretty girl in one direction, then his steps will tend to go in that direction and he will go a distance proportional to \(n\). In a lifetime of many, many independent choices, small and large, a career with a vision will get you a distance proportional to \(n\), while no vision will get you only the distance \(\sqrt n\).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would be “Oh you don’t need to understand maths to get the message.” Another would be “It’s essential that you understand how Hamming makes that conclusion and you should not do anything prior to that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, reverse that advice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/30</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/30</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What does that button do?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At work, I get to click a button, wait 5 minutes and see my work deployed in either test, UAT or production environment. With almost no stress that something infrastructural can go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our DevOps team is telling us that we will have to think less about this process in near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am growing curious: What does that button do, exactly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there are two buttons. One is “pressed” by a webhook from Github (I think?) and builds and stores a Docker image. The other then actually does the deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The container is built through this steps, noted down verbosely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Initialize job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pre-job
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Download pgp dev&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Download pgp data&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Download sops file&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;helm package&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checkout git repository&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensure PGP key installed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construct version number&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fetch tags&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set the Helm Chart version on on values-*.json&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update dependencies
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;test [environment]&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;uat [environment]&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;upload: Helm folder&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean Docker cache&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Docker login&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate Helm charts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download: helm charts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove unnecessary files&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Override deployment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helm lint&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helm package&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build an image&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push the image&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push to chart museum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push to chart museum prod&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Publish artifact: environments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update patch numberin variable group&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean agent directories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post-job:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;clean agent directories&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;helm package&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Checkout gitrepository (??)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the deployment is done through these steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Initialize job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pre-job
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Download pgp dev&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Download pgp data&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download artifact - build - environments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download artifact - build - full-helm-chart&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensure PGP key installed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deploy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finalize job&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/29</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/29</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On &quot;The Art of Doing Science and Engineering&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Books written for a different audience are hard to read. I don’t belong to the wide audience of Hamming’s “The Art of Doing Science and Engineering.” I admit parts of the book cost me way too much time. So you can imagine the comfort I felt when I read that I could skip the maths:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Later sections will be understandable […]. General results are always stated in words […]”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept on reading. The book is about “style”, after all. I am interested in his general results. It did, however, hurt a bit to read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Later sections will be understandable provided you are willing to forgo the deep insights mathematics gives into the weaknesses of our current beliefs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first chapter of the book is titled “Orientation.” which gives a good taste of Hamming’s style: a delightful mix of a mathematically clear mind, self-help a la The Art of Manliness, and eloquently delivered life advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick glance and I see that many are attracted to one of the latter, rather than for the mathematically clear mind. For I came across quotes from the self-help (for researchers?) bits, &lt;a href=&quot;https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2021/03/22/richard-hammings-the-art-of-doing-science-and-engineering/&quot;&gt;Andrew Gelman expressing unfulfilled career desires&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/3746698/the-art-of-doing-science-and-engineering-back-of-the-envelope-math&quot;&gt;one person who asked a question on StackExchange&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll consider the following self-evident: you should not read quotes from a book on “style”. Gelman’s discovery is both useful to him, and gives you a hint on how you can become Gelman’s student, if you’re into that sort of thing. I’ll focus on the question on StackExchange. (A message to the writer of the question: I hope this helps you enjoy it more the next time. My purpose is not to discourage you from picking up the book again, or cause any other emotional distress.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the examples of this chapter is an illustration of how to quickly evaluate two well-specified hypothesis. This is an important example, because, again, “Style of thinking is the center of the course.” and it is the style that allows the evaluation. It is the style that is on display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The style is elaborate enough for 227 pages from Hamming, I won’t even try to summarise it. Here’s an example, though:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I will take […] two statements, knowledge doubles every 17 years, and 90% of the scientists who ever lived are now alive, and ask to what extent they are compatible. The model of the growth of knowledge and the growth of scientists assumed are both exponential, with the growth of knowledge being proportional to the number of scientists alive. We begin by assuming the number scientists at any time t is
\(y(t) = ae^{bt}\)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may feel like you’re missing something obvious, like the original poster: “What’s a? What’s T? I assume e is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E_(mathematical_constant)&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; guy.” Then you need to listen to Hamming. I recommend you make sure you can parse the paragraph into the formula with the help of a pen and a paper. (And yes, the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;e&lt;/code&gt; is that guy, as it will very, very frequently be. Consider making it a habit to try to full in that guy each time you see &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;e&lt;/code&gt; in math before asking it. You may end up thinking faster.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may seem like too much effort, but consider trying how long it takes you to evaluate those statements with full confidence in your result. And think whether you could express your method with extreme precision to many thousands of people in half a page like Manning does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the journey!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t forget - “Do not think the technical content is the course—it is only illustrative material.” But you better understand the illustrations really well, if you’re to learn “style” from a book.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/26</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/26</guid>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The sense of a bean sprout</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“[…] if you have the sense of a bean sprout you know you’re in a rare and irreproducible presence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analogy is obvious, it’s just been lying there for someone to reach at it. Only one person &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=%22sense+of+a+bean+sprout%22&amp;amp;client=firefox-b-d&amp;amp;ei=fCODYJPRLP2H9u8Pvs-PuA0&amp;amp;oq=%22sense+of+a+bean+sprout%22&amp;amp;gs_lcp=Cgdnd3Mtd2l6EAMyCAghEBYQHRAeOgcIABBHELADUPAUWJ0fYIYhaAFwAngAgAFPiAHfAZIBATOYAQCgAQGqAQdnd3Mtd2l6yAEIwAEB&amp;amp;sclient=gws-wiz&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiT__ehkJXwAhX9g_0HHb7nA9cQ4dUDCA0&amp;amp;uact=5&quot;&gt;seems to have done it&lt;/a&gt;, Ursula K. LeGuin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She concludes the following paragraph with that sentence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If memory remains sound and the thinking mind retains its vigor, an old intelligence may have extraordinary breadth and depth of understanding. It’s had time to gather knowledge and more practice in comparison and judgement. No matter if the knowledge is intellectual or practical or emotional, if it concerns alpine ecosystems or the Buddha nature or how to reassure a frightened child: when you meet an old person with that kind of knowledge, if you have the sense of a bean sprout you know you’re in a rare and irreproducible presence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/23</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/23</guid>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Worth Noticing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I use Beeminder to track a few goals. Some of these are quite essential for my wellbeing, some aren’t (like my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beeminder.com/oguzhanogreden/w-daily&quot;&gt;commitment to write these daily notes&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me a really long while to realise one area where Beeminder really shines: It functions perfectly as a trigger for you to notice things. That goal you said you’d stick to? Well, you haven’t. And it won’t just fade into background, it will take 5 bucks from your wallet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/22</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/22</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Shell Culture</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After years of “having to” and “fighting with”, I’m finally grokking shell scripting, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While trying to get &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/oguzhanogreden/dotfiles/blob/master/scripts/bmndr-tmin.sh&quot;&gt;a shell script&lt;/a&gt; to work on OhMyZsh. I vaguely though of a  scene from Where Wizards Stay Up Late. The main difference between the experience of the developers described there and my experience was that I never had to think of a “LOGIN” to be truncated to “LO” due to network issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never had to think of my programs as a stream of characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when I read the comment “Sorry, I should have thought about echoing the contents of course.” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/275797&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), it just made sense.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/20</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/20</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Two Histories, and Another One</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notion.so/Broad-Band-by-Claire-L-Evans-a1ec6dffff4940d6852e071210f0910e&quot;&gt;Broad Band&lt;/a&gt; by Claire L. Evans right after Where the Wizards Stay Up Late has been interesting so far. There’s a lot to of good things to be said about Broad Band, and I may do that once I’m through the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most striking differences is how they chose their frames. Reading Where Wizards Stay Up Late, you get to know two groups of people: the mighty wizards and the powerful man. It’s as much the story of the powerful man who paved a way as it is about mighty wizards who marched the paved path in their own inspiring, awkward and adorable manner. You get to imagine an ARPA director providing millions of dollars of funding. You get to forget the literal army of people that made this possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading Broad Band, you get the taste of a different story. It’s a balancing act. There are pointers to existing histories of the wizards, but you’re reading a &lt;em&gt;wider&lt;/em&gt; history. One in which women who had to persevere through sexism in some of its most hideous forms is at the center of the stage. You read stories of women who had to embrace a horrible kind of grind. Next to the very familiar kind of grind &lt;a href=&quot;https://jacobian.org/2021/apr/7/embrace-the-grind/&quot;&gt;that makes things possible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--[202104122020 Embrace the Grind] --&gt;, that makes them happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s then disappointing a bit when you see other faces through lines that you were just allowed to forget. When efforts that helped commit one of the most horrorful atrocities of our history gets credited as “saving time and lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/19</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/19</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How could I have done this for times faster?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s the end of my first week with &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/02/20/pivot-career-software/&quot;&gt;my new team&lt;/a&gt;. Towards the end of the week, I came across a Tweet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why couldn’t we deliver this 4 times faster is a good question for software development teams to be asking.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t find the Tweet, but If I recall correctly, the author meant to suggest this as a question that would help developers stretch their imagination and focus on their tooling. I took it a bit differently: It’s not a stretch for me to imagine that I will soon produce four times what I’ve produced this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at my week with this lens, what were the time sinkholes for me? Two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve tested my solutions too many times.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I hadn’t read the documentation of my dependencies well enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tested too many times primarily because conjuring a mental “infinite zoom overview” of my work has been difficult. Both on the backend with microservices and in the frontend with Angular, this slowed me down prohibitively. This was compounded by the fact that I’m far from having a solid knowledge of the many specifics of external dependencies, frameworks and in-house solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading documentation in a rushed way is a classic, of course. This was a case of “I just want this damn thing to be done” and I should’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/04/11/very-recently/&quot;&gt;known better&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--[[202104112132 (very) recently - post]]--&gt;. There isn’t much to do but to remind yourself that this does not save time, after all. Reading documentation may also be the only way to get confident with specifics of everything.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/17</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/17</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Presence, Absence, Computing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(I thought this would become something better, it didn’t work out, but I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beeminder.com/oguzhanogreden/w-daily&quot;&gt;a promise&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A non-controversial statement: Computing is about references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d like to refer to something that exists and do something with it. Now you can’t stop there: You need to be able to refer to non-existence, null. Maybe you are someone who can think of 0 as something other than a reference to non-existence. If you need to represent something electrically (utimately), you will need first and foremost have to distinguish presence and absence of electricity. If you find yourself in the sad profession of representing things electrically, you will realise that you need to give up. Forget about all those “other things 0 can be.” You will call “that doesn’t exist” 0 and “that exists” 1, and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have 1, and 0 so that you can have 1, you have infinitely many references that you can use. That you are using.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/16</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/16</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>No-CV</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For years, one of the most prominent elements on this page has been a link to my CV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, the same will be there but will read “no-CV” and will link to this page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This comes from the realization that when I think of my CV, I think of a different thing than most. I would like to take &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; to my work. As this is my “CV”, it makes more sense for me to link you to it: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ozan.ogreden.com&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, which isn’t in a good state, but that’s not how it will stay!bb&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/15</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ozan.ogreden.com/notebook/2021/04/15</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
